[music]
society, we welcome everyone to the live
recording of the currently untitled podcast in
Ivano-Frankivsk And it is simply a great
joy to talk with you about important
topics for us And to invite you to our
audio living room We are not the first time to
find ourselves on such an absolutely welcoming
carpet with you Nastya and we
really feel very intimate and very
private so that Our conversation about
Ukrainian culture and culture in general
is as frank as possible, but at the same time
We always know that you, our
listeners, are with us, and therefore I hope that today
everything will be successful and today we can address
not fictional people but to very
real material ones and actually then
ask about something if you have
questions You can of course ask them at the end
So our 19th episode on the topic
How do we speak can we have one conversation about
one language and this question how do we speak
We took it from the work of Boris
Antonenko Davydovich, which was published in
1970 and is a work about the Ukrainian language
and its purity. So this work is in the introduction
Antonenko Davidovych explains that there are many
different expressions about the language of various artists and
Karl Marquez, including, well, he had
to write, he had to write in the 70s, the publishing house was a
Soviet writer, but in the end he
writes about the fact that the struggle for purity and
high linguistic culture is the struggle for
culture. Antonenko
Davydovych then lists that
scientists, linguists, writers, journalists,
teachers must work to ensure that
their language is clean, work
on speaking Ukrainian, writing in
Ukrainian, articulating it so that
millions of readers, listeners, viewers
eventually receive a quality product because
only in the hands of these media professionals and
teachers female teachers that the
language should
be alive So that it sounds
and fills the space with the right
words and the right wording, here it is
not only about the correct pronunciation, although it is
primarily about it
in the public space
since independence, the Ukrainian language
began
to appear actively not so long ago at the
legislative level, it began to
first regulate the law of 2006,
which
worked to ensure that
Ukrainian language dubbing appeared in all movie theaters
, and then the next step. This was the
year 2021, January 16, a law that we often
refer to when it comes to the Ukrainian
language in public space and once upon
a time Last year, in the summer,
Bohdana and I went to a trendy
new establishment in Podil. We sat, drank
wine and ate something for a while. It was great, we had a great
conversation, but there was one problem. We were
served in Russian, and Bohdana and I
were very determined, so we got up and
approached the administrator. who
asked the question why your institution does not
comply with the law on language,
some administrator tried so hard to
avoid the answer and there
will be millions of such stories who started to say Well, you
understand, we work with older
people, the average age of a waiter is 20 years, we
work with older people, it is so
difficult for them to transition and some more
blah blah blah in the end We didn't hear
any position
but left there can be a million such stories and I am
sure that there are a million of them because the law
on speech in public space is not
enforced
Bohdana here should be either some
example from your life or something else you have to
pick it up somehow I have a few
corrections because the listeners are prompt So for
now without a name, they know that I have a
legal education and I still want to
say that we also have the Constitution of
Ukraine, this is a document from the year 1996, in which
the Ukrainian language is said quite
succinctly, article 10 speaks the state
language in Ukraine, there is a Ukrainian language, full
stop about the provision of this language,
and the problem is that we really
did not have legislation for a very long time. We would
decide what this provision should look like
, and the law on the language was
adopted as far back as the 19th year, but
its individual provisions
gradually came into force, and
that is why we for a very long time, for example, we have not seen a
Ukrainian gloss in Ukrainian
today it sounds paradoxical And in
some ways even funny Ukrainian gloss in
Russian But
it was a very staged process and I
tried to see what the
history of this Article 10 of the Constitution of
Ukraine was in general, because it would seem that we have said everything: the
Constitution of Ukraine, the state language is
Ukrainian. It is one, but there were even
several decisions of the Constitutional Court
Regarding this articles, and one of them was
precisely the complaints of people's deputies about the
non-use of the Ukrainian language by people who
perform state functions, that is,
most likely other deputies, or that I don't
want to talk for a very long time about all kinds of
legal nuances, but I am happy that
when we talk with you today and that there is an
episode that will be released on August 23, on the Day of the State
Flag of Ukraine and on the eve of Ukrainian Independence Day.
I think that for most of our listeners it
will sound simply absurd. That is, we
are talking about some archaisms when we
talk about the
efforts of the Russian language, about
service in the Russian language, about the
Russian language in literature about
the Russian language in the press, in the media, so
certain things are left Yes, but I am convinced
that the further they go, the more atevistic,
outdated and not modern they
will look, but it is important to say that this
was not always the case and until recently it was completely
different, Bohdana, I am glad when your
legal education is useful to
you and me. How am I, Bohdana, but
still despite that that the war is going on, and discussions are going
on for some reason, for some reason, discussions are going
on about this language Is she alone or is she
not alone, although you and I know the answer
and in particular This is a discussion about two
media personalities yes, yes, I am talking about Masha
Efrosinina and Olya Polyakov, this is
show business news
show business news, I have such an episode in
my life. When I was a teacher at an
all-Ukrainian school online during the
quarantine, and then I had different stars come to our lessons and I
taught Ukrainian literature lessons
so that they would sit
instead of children, and once there was even such a
show on Nova channels,
episodes of a fifth grader are smarter, well, in a word, the essence of the
presence of the stars was for them
to prove that No, they are not smarter than
fifth graders it was just a joke
, they didn't laugh at it, and then
Masha Yefrosinina and Olya Polyakova came to see me.
Masha Yefrosi, at Lesya Ukrainka's lesson on the forest song, was
very moved by
Mavka's fate and was very confused by everything she was talking about
, and then she saw what
I had I had many other books with
me, we are not blunt studies of Ukrainian poetry from
the Baba Galamaga publishing house, some other
books that I used, from which I
read in class, she took photos of all these books,
she made stories, she
wanted to buy them and asked me to
drop her where they can be purchased and so it's
similar and if there was such a lively,
cool dialogue, she was so interested in
what to interest Olya Polyakova, it was a
more difficult question because why did you choose I
chose what the
Sentimental Poetry of
Mykola Voronyi program offered to me Mykola Voronyi is just a
good poet for Olya Polyakova because he is a
simple rhythmic lyrics, you can imagine that
you, when you dance or sing on stage,
you also have a certain rhythm. Well, in the
case of
M it worked for Voronoi, too, or it did
n't work because Olya Polyakova was very
enthusiastic and our lesson lasted 12
minutes longer than it should have, of course, then it was
cut short, but she was impressed, she
wanted to read more of these texts, I believed
that maybe she would put, for example,
about the eyes of the night to the music, but it didn't happen,
but it's still ahead.
Actually, then it seemed to me that
these two young ladies are answering in
Ukrainian, they're singing in Ukrainian,
they're preparing some product in Ukrainian,
but a video appears, raise your hand. Who
understands what kind of scandal we're talking about now?
for those who do not understand for this
minority, but we will explain because this is
show business news, we have such a function to explain
Masha Yefrosinina and Olya Polyakova have
their own YouTube show, which has half a million
subscribers, and in this YouTube show they
continue to host it in Russian, they
are being hated in the comments, how does it
happen, and at some point they recorded a
video message about the fact that we will not
switch to Ukrainian, because we have
several arguments, firstly, we cannot
express our emotions in Ukrainian, this is
already absurd, and secondly, because this is
a conversation between two girlfriends in the kitchen.
speak as we want in whatever language we want
and there is no need to try to limit us
but they forget that they are
media persons their channel of communication
Even if it is private YouTube and is not
closed to a limited circle of
users but open it is also a
public sphere and it also obliges
to implement the law on language, God bless you, do you
want to comment? I want to do it.
Finally, you commented, you
want to ask me a question for the second time. And I still don't
understand. What is your attitude, because you
very sympathetically described to us your
experience of working with Olya Polakovka
Mashina Efrosinina. Now I don't understand
do you sympathize with them Do you want to speak out
against I sympathize with us that we
observe such
inexperienced unknown persons
spend so much time on our TV
screens and YouTube screens,
because in her video, Emma
Antonyuk on the channel Palaye M. Antonyuk communicated very well
exactly this problem, the
problem of these two gentlemen about the fact that there are
linguistic needs of Ukrainian-speaking
Ukrainians, and therefore Russified Ukrainians
must
satisfy the needs of
Ukrainian-speakers You see Ukrainians so
difficult, said Bohdana. You understood what
I said. Well, Masha Efrosinina should
speak Ukrainian. In short, in the
public space, my question
to you is how you feel about this situation.
And what do you think about the
Ukrainian-speaking Ukrainian space
around us?
I generally had two
reactions, the
first was so uncontrollable and emotional, and the
second was already when I steamed up this
situation a little, and actually this uncontrolled
reaction was that I thought,
God, why am I even hearing this, it is very
obscene Thank you, in general, it is possible today
in the context of the war in the context all
that about the experience that Ukrainian
society is going through and, in the end, these two women also
try to protect the Russian language and
look for arguments for this. It just
causes discomfort. And at this moment, when
you witness something like this, you
want to somehow leave the room, but then
I started thinking about what
you said is that there are people who just
privately under anonymous avatars
express their not always useful thoughts
in their twitters or their tiny
instagrams. And there is a completely different situation in another
situation when such speech is conducted by
people who shape trends because
certain trends may not be formed
for you and me, for example, the
stars of Ukrainian show business, but
they are definitely forming for
many viewers and listeners in the
same Masha Efrosina, this is a very young
audience and a part of this audience is
exactly those people, career building is ahead of them,
not behind, that is, in Masha
Yefrosinina has a very specific career on
television, which created her face,
brand and image. I have a career in
cool projects, and people look at her
as a model of behavior, as a
model from which they can take an example, and they
will think whether I need to
practice Ukrainian in order to
be successful. Can I, for example,
maneuver or choose Russian?
who spoke and I was told
this to you once. In this
Russian podcast, you can reach a larger
audience, and this problem is a problem for me
in general, because it articulates poorly.
This is what I want
to tell a different story, it will probably also be
show business news, sorry, we will move on to
others For example, I was touched by a video
that appeared in the New York Times about
a month and a half ago, and we will add a link to
it in the description of this episode. It was a
conversation between a New York Times correspondent and
Ivan Dorn.
how Ivan Dorn feels now,
who has to reinvent his
identity. He has many problems with
himself. He has many problems with himself his
behavior to his career to his language
and we can all understand Ivan Dorn and
in principle we can easily list from a
line where these questions
come from. He grew up in the photographs of Sasha Maslova
wonderful portraits Ivan Dorn is somewhat
depressed with a hunchback and we see that
he really thinks very hard about
his future. Perhaps he is even
suffering in parallel. A New
York Times correspondent writes to us about the only
Russian-speaking music market that
existed, where everyone loved each other very much, listened well,
visited each other at the
same festival, performed, but then,
as we understand, the war came and everything
changes, and there is someone like Ivan Dorn or, as it
is written, the correspondent of Svitlana Lobod,
and now they have to look for new
positions.
I was incredibly annoyed by this article
because, in my opinion, it
describes an absolutely marginal case in the Ukrainian context,
because we all know that on
Andrii Khlyvnyuk is now at the front, who
defends Ukraine and the right of
Ukrainians with weapons zikants to write in
Ukrainian and make Ukrainian music.
We know what Svyatoslav
Vakarchuk Taras Topolya does. We
know a lot of musicians, somewhat
less well-known bands who are also in the
Teroboron or in the Armed Forces of Ukraine
and they have no problems with Ukrainian
identity, moreover, they are very
cool with it articulate how interesting
Andrii Khlyvnyuk's problematic poetry is now, which
he sometimes shares in his stories. But the
correspondent of the York Times, who worked
in the Moscow Bureau, does not consider it appropriate to
talk to Andrii Khlyvnyuk, and
he also does not want to talk to Vakarchuk, who
at first greatly helped volunteers and the
armed forces today he performs at an
event, performs a concert and collects money again.
No, he decides that it is more interesting for him to
talk about this little thing that arises in the
mind of Ivan Dorn, and this is a big problem for me.
When we talk about the
perception of the Ukrainian language and
Ukrainian culture on the outside, because it is
absolutely not representative but the story is
different Mr rava What exactly this New
York Times article shows is how stories are
magnetizing, and this story with Masha
Yefrosinina and Olga Polakova is
quite similar to what I
talked about in the context of the New York Times,
because fortunately you and I do not understand
one or the other This is not our problem, we
know how to work in Ukrainian. We did not
work in Russian and we do not now
revise our identity in the
way they do, but it is
incredibly attractive to many and not
only those who hesitate.
recognition of the impossibility of transition, because
there are indeed people who used
Russian as their permanent tool and for
decades we wrote articles in it,
worked on television, sang how
to deal with them, I think that this is a much more difficult
question, which you have to learn to
answer, how do you answer it, I
answer that there are
Russified Ukrainians who are Russified
due to many different circumstances
and someone is to blame Oh, he has a
Russian grandfather, and I have a Russian grandfather, for example, and
I have a Russian surname. Well, when it
is written through the letter And it is
fortunately. Thank you to the passport officers, it is written
through the letter and I feel very
Ukrainian.
guilty that
their grandfather spoke Russian, their
grandmother, mother, father, no, it's not just the
circumstances, they turned out that way, but
time passed and these circumstances changed, they
changed in 1991, I want to remind you that
enough time has passed in 30 years, you can
already accept that the Ukrainian
language is the state language more in
ukrainization
happened so gently in Ukraine and
continues to happen and is it easy to
pump up six cubes of the press
someone pumped up from the present 6 cubes of the
press from zero
to the word it is not easy
if you tried That is, you need
to exercise regularly monitor
nutrition go to bed follow the
regime and that need to be done for a
long time to make those abs
appear or simply quit smoking Well, for
sure, avid smokers will tell you that it is not
easy and you also need to make an effort or
just learn English, what do you do?
Pass the test, that is Full and Mother level B2
or is it one and was to communicate on a level
with a native speaker No, it is not easy, it also
requires practice exercises and if you
asked us that And what is the best way to learn how to
better learn how to approach learning
English I said Well you
watch the series Friends for example
in English You read
English books you listen to podcasts
in English and you would say Yes we
do it and it is difficult You guys you are
on the way to improving your
level of English,
all the same, but we apply it to the Ukrainian
language, too, Ukrainian becomes your
everyday language, the language of your smartphone, the language of
the TV series and movies you watch, you
gradually discover for yourself, so here I
am leading to a thesis about that
Russified Ukrainians are not to blame for the fact that
they are like that, but they could and should
make efforts to change to go on and on
like this, according to the language principle, the division will still
take place and it will continue because the language of the
Ukrainian state is the Ukrainian
language. institutions
within the company when you are at work
on YouTube Instagram in Russian as
soon as it disappears, the
possibility to share will disappear I would really
like to return to this metaphor
that you spoke about, metaphors of the gym and
actually metaphors of habit, a lot of
people today really choose the
Ukrainian language for various reasons and are far from
it's always career because in many
areas you don't need to
know Ukrainian so perfectly and meticulously to do
your job. But for them it can be a
private choice related to the fact that
Russia attacked Ukraine and the Russian language
is the language of death the language of genocide and the language of
murderers. But it seems to me that very often
we talk about all kinds of crimes goes from language
to language as if about something like that, it's as if he
clicked with his fingers, so he clicked. And
that's not really the case, and it's also a cliché of
Russian propaganda that Ukrainian
is very closely organized, for example,
to Russian, or that it turns out that it's
not so close for For many people, it is
incredibly difficult to switch from Russian
to Ukrainian, and for some, it
can really take years and years to do it,
and I think that this is also an important topic to
talk about, that you need practice in
order for everything to be elastic and beautiful, and it
really happens that you speak Russian.
you could. And Ukrainian is not so. My friend is a
fundraiser. He told me recently. He
switched to Ukrainian a few
months ago and says, you know. I understand
that I speak English better than I
speak Ukrainian now, even though I can
hear everyday conversation, it was
absolutely OK and I Avzhezh praised him,
but I caught myself thinking that
I had always been like that. I always
spoke English better than Russian, but for
me it was la some kind of conscious history,
because I didn’t come across Russian at
school and at the university anymore, I knew
it passively and read some literature in it, but it
was never my language of use on my
tongue, so I know that I can take it and
speak and now I’m sure
it would even be easier to
speak Polish than Russian, but I am leading to
the point that I am
ready to understand those who
really struggle with these processes and it
is very important to have quite different
entry points into the language and to understand these possible
mechanisms, moreover, to see
success stories I think it is very
important that some people share their
transition stories. Two stories immediately come to mind.
The first is the story
of the famous Kyiv architect Balbek,
who is also slowly transitioning, but he
tells how he surrounds himself in
Ukrainian.
also
consciously chose the Ukrainian language and also
slowly surrounds himself with it in order to
enrich his vocabulary I read
Ukrainian poetry to
Bohdan, do you want a coming out? I always
suspect that I will ask Dima to cut it out.
But maybe not because it
will definitely be preserved for everyone present here
until the age of 14.
In my life, there was a Russian language. I
spoke Russian three times a week.
When I went to dances, I spoke
Russian. with my friends in the yard, I
spoke in Russian with the godfather and
godmother and friends of my parents
who often appeared in my
life and on September
1 of the 9th grade When I came to study at the
Ukrainian Humanitarian Lyceum and in the
first lesson my class teacher and
then my colleague and my friend Ms.
Valentina explained to me and explained to us all
why in this lyceum
among the rules is to speak only
Ukrainian. Who were the founders of the lyceum?
What are the ideological foundations on which we are all here?
What did you call us, the future elite of the nation?
a common
practice among
nationalistically conscious educational
institutions, and then she made a decision for
herself I'm starting to play by these
rules. I'm a lyceum student of this lyceum who
sang the national anthem of Ukraine every morning.
that is, you can imagine that there were friends with whom you
communicated in Russian in previous years. So
you start speaking Ukrainian. Well, I'll
be honest, I can't imagine. That is, I don't have
this experience. Well, you can imagine. And you're
still 14 years old and you have many other
problems in this life, which can have a
child at the age of 14, in a
word, I am very proud of myself as a
little 14-year-old now from this height
because I understand that this was a very important
step that simply determined my position and
since then the position has not wavered anywhere.
I think that these stories about
children teenage elections they are actually
very important and they give us a lot it's
cool when they are because I remember a little
different story from my childhood but I
remember how I I was wondering what to say.
Hello, this is kind of stupid, it's not cool. Hello,
you have to say it. Yes, hello, hello.
I have
this feeling today. This is the feeling of not being classy,
and in fact it is a
colonial legacy, that is where I am from, a girl
in Lviv, a little girl, in fact,
that is, I was 5-6 years old, I must have
had this feeling that it is not classy, ​​that is,
you have to say Hi, not Hello. That's why
Hello. This is some kind of stupidity
on much larger examples, it
can be analyzed from the stories of friends and
even me. It is a pity that we
did not analyze some stories and did not collect them from our
readers on Instagram.
today to absorb it, that is, I
For example, I really want to use one single example in all conversations
about the Ukrainian language,
which inspires me a lot,
I thought about it a few days
before the escalation, you probably remember, there was
such a huge wave of transitions to the Ukrainian language,
and I somehow remembered that in the
Ukrainian generation of the twenties, 100
years ago, there were a lot of people who
made their debut in Russian and then consciously
chose Ukrainian, and these were not some marginalized people.
This is Mykola Khvylovy This is Mykola
Zerov this is Dry Cloud Mykhailo this is Mike
Johansen who writes in a humorous
questionnaire that I do not live in Rostov when he is
asked why you are a Ukrainian
writer and write in Ukrainian and this
naturalness of such humorous and in some ways
daring answers is for me very
attractive. I really want these
examples, also because I understand that when
we list such names as the one I just
listed, we are talking about whole
figures of Ukrainian literature. That is,
they are people who have enriched it lexically, in particular, even
now. When I listen to my friends who are
switching to Ukrainian, then I understand that
they try this language on their tongue in a completely
different way than I do and when I am sometimes quite
n to speak formally, they can
use a certain word in a
third context, a
third dictionary meaning, but to
revive it, to give it to this word, I
will hear it and see how it
works, and in fact, those people who today,
especially in the creative class, are switching
to Ukrainian, they are incredibly enriching
Ukrainian language and there is no trauma here.
This is just a story of creation and it is. I
like it very much, that's why I
watch these people with interest because,
again, I understand what they will add to
this language and eventually add to me as a
person who works with it.
I think God it's time
to remember why
it is important
to protect the Ukrainian language
pathetic wording to protect the Ukrainian
language, but
why are they killing it Who cares if we don't protect it and by
chance I will quote Ivan
Malkovych let's not be forbidden words,
let it be possible and not the most important thing But you, a
child, are called to protect the
tiny candle of the letter with your palms and
also stretched out on the fingers
about erigat lunar crescent letters There is something
cut from the sky together with a string because
they say, child, what is the language of our nightingale They
say it well, but then we wonder that someday there
may come such times when our
language will not be remembered even by the smallest
nightingale, so you can't rely
only on Nightingales.
Such a gentle poem to a child. Yes, I love it too.
By the way, it is
just right for
not so gentle, although gently, but very
defiantly performed by Viktor Morozov. He doesn't
often sing this song, but there it is so
very playful and you don't have
that feeling. dangers Well, listen
Malkovich knew what he was writing about and when he
worked as an editor in a publishing house in the
youth of the 80s, he also understood the place of
this Ukrainian language in the context of
Russified Kyiv and Well, to pretend that he
was not like this Kyiv is spitting in one's
eyes that is, you also have to tell the truth,
but it is great luck that the situation is changing.
Listen, I recently reread a fairy tale that
I really liked in my childhood
by Ivan Malkovich, which
is called the golden spider is a
short fairy tale. And this is a fairy tale that
tells about a very happy
family. One day, the father of this family goes
to war with them because his country was
attacked by the Northern neighbor
from childhood. I don't remember this
fragment, but when I reread it,
I think his lords, that is, in the 90s,
Malkovich, having founded the publishing house
Ababagalamaga, thought that such a
small Bohdan should put into his head the
idea that there is a Northern neighbor.
there are generally nice children's texts
that have, well, we can say today such
an absolutely patriotic direction, and it is another
matter that this is a patriotic direction.
Also, in our country, it was often branded as
some kind of excessive or obscene, but it is
just a normal preventive one, and it is
not even necessarily an occasion to think, because a child
will not sit and think about it,
but the child will remember it and the child will
remember, say, some illustrations or
what is in this Golden Spider I remember
the war is over we won dad
came home And brought a gift he
came back for Christmas Eve when the family is
sitting really without money and
no way Set the table and everything is fine Everything
should be fine I like it very much
this is the coding of the space that Malkovich does,
and listen, let's talk about the
coding of the Ukrainian-speaking space,
because a lot of people today
remember Ivan Malkovich as such a key
figure for this, because in many
cities of Ukraine, for a very long time,
ababagalamag books could be the only
Ukrainian-language publications that a
child could buy and Malkovich took the fact that
they were the most beautiful and Dityna simply
pointed with her fingers and said I want this
Snow Queen I want the alphabet I want my
favorite poems or there was such a series of
happily small books for hryvnia that
everyone could afford, they
were sold at Ukrposhta, even people from the
Crimea or from Luhansk remember that they
were always these books And this would sometimes it's
not the only way to immerse yourself in the Ukrainian
language. What else do you think about? You started
talking about how Ukrainian
film dubbing appeared, it also seems
epochal to me. And you shouldn't underestimate this,
because everyone talked for a long time about the fact that, well,
what kind of cinema in Ukrainian dub a
movie in Ukrainian, what? And Oleksa
Negrebetskyi came and everything just flowed in the
same way in Ukrainian. It seemed to me that it should
have been, for example, Esquier magazine when
it appeared in Ukraine.
in Ukrainian, when I
bought it, then this first issue
was a wonder for me too, that
in the Ukrainian media space,
a square finally appeared, and what is it, Square, in
what positions will it be in the Ukrainian
space? Well, I think that it should be here
The passage about the renaming of streets, but I
think that we will benefit from this
Bohdan, did you vote in Kyiv
digitally for the renaming of streets in the
city of Kyiv Yes, I confess, ches but I
didn't vote because there were 300 names, more than 300,
it was too much, that is, because I didn't
just point my finger at any name.
I also googled who the
expert commission advises. And who was the
finalist, because the choice had to be conscious And
this renaming had to be aware of this in
order to understand what kind of relationship
certain people had with these places, it is
also very important to have this link.
it was a great opportunity Bohdan, what a
very, very cool opportunity it was. To be honest,
it was the first dismantled Bulgakov in
Kyiv. Nastya and I really want Kyiv
to stop being the clichéd city of Mikhail
Bulgakov and to be the city of Valerian
Pidmogilny. For us, Kyiv has long been the
city of Valerian Pidmogilny, but he
in our opinion, it should become so for everyone and
in popular culture in particular, and if you
cut it short, they dismantled the board from the
yellow case of your native yellow
case and nothing. lo we fell out
brut, I drank a bit cheaper than brut But
these are already details,
the same about the streets, it is already very important
because it encodes our space, we walk down one
street and go to another, and when this
street is Chervonoarmiiska, there is a
certain dissonance, just like with
Elenyana Street but if we delve further, then
Lermontov or Turgenev. Let's talk
about popular culture, because this is what
really Ukrainianizes the space and Ukrainianizes
everyone, because it normalizes the Ukrainian language,
again, many people remember the
Ukrainian-speaking period 1+1 as a time when
you wanted to do everything in this language because the
pluses were so cool that you wanted to be
like on television and agreed on
magazines. It is also very important to me
that today the gloss will be in Ukrainian
because for a very long time we understood that,
for example, we cannot read about fashion in
Ukrainian simply because there are no
materials about Ukrainian fashion there are the
best glossy magazines, they were
Russian-language.
and to the music with what
creak they went, so there were a lot of conversations
about what they were saying. But how much of this music
and no one will type it, but it was a
question of the market, and a lot of players
just started making content in Ukrainian.
Because they accept this question of the market, and
I think that in fact very cool, when there is a
regulator,
you and I talked about such emotional
things for quite a long time.
the attitude towards him
if you are not a lawyer in constitutional law is
not easy to say the least, but when there is a law,
there is a norm that regulates certain
legal relations. For example, when we children
were sitting in a Kyiv restaurant and understood
that we had a question about the language of service, it
was not our Quirk and we did not have to
overcome internal discomfort due to the fact that
a person who speaks Russian because it is
her native language and she probably has the
right I am happy that this law is
in effect, that its provisions are consistently
coming into force, and that a certain
framework is emerging in which the Ukrainian language functions,
because of course, when we talk about
literature, when we talk about music,
we are talking about something very private, what is
going on
from the inside, and even if you choose,
for example, Ukrainian as opposed to
Russian, it is still an internal
choice, but when it comes to the
public sphere, there must be
this framework, otherwise
conflicts begin, simply
solving questions begins.
which
came and which simply did not exist, which will greatly
affect the space around us, you
started talking about the Ukrainian language in the
space around And I thought about the fact that
the group Vremya y Steklo only had
one song in the Ukrainian language and they
broke up, they are not related to each other things,
but it is good that it took place, well, that is,
they already got on the radio according to quotas,
I would like everyone to get on the radio,
we and quotas,
but maybe I will make a lesson aside to another
question, a question that we were asked at
our Kyiv Laiv, and then we
promised that we will have an episode about the
language soon, we will definitely talk about it,
about the transition to Ukrainian,
such a pressing question, what is the topic, what is the topic
shared by bloggers those who switched, you
mentioned the glory of Balbek, there is a very
cool article by
literature teacher Artur Proydakov about 10
steps of switching to the Ukrainian language, he
advises, in particular, to watch the series Friends in
Ukrainian, well, that is, I
already said this half an hour ago, but I am ready
to repeat it once more
a project from Prometheus, a course of 27 lessons of the
Ukrainian language, and when public PE was
organized from the First
National, it became public, one of the
first projects they had was a
life hack in Ukrainian, has anyone seen this
program Dmytro Horkin, the host is a very
cool program, these are short sketches
where two pairs of men act out and a
woman. Sometimes they are neighbors, colleagues,
random
passers-by who play certain games and language
situations and then the voice of the presenter of
Ukrainian radio Dmytro Horkin explains
this rule in an accessible way with examples so that
you can learn
it easily, cool, beautiful, high-quality Production
This is exactly how we should be told about the
rules of the Ukrainian language so that we
think about how we speak, the question is what
put on Antonenko and the spectacle
And that's when we were asked on the Kyiv bench
What books would you recommend reading to
those who intend to improve their
Ukrainian Bohdana What books would you
recommend to those who intend to improve
their Ukrainian and enrich their
vocabulary Oh, this
may be a long answer I I advise you to read
modern Ukrainian writers who write in a lively and
lively language in order to choose who
you like. You can take the short
lists of the BBC Book of the Year award and
look at the prose and choose what you
like, because there will be detective stories and
romance novels, and it is very difficult.
multi-layered literature there you can
find very different texts and most of
them are written very cool and at the same time very
different Ukrainian
I advise everyone to look for their favorite voices
because I remember that we speak in
Ivano-Frankivsk and it would be a sin not to mention
Yuriy Andruhovych when I
discovered poetry about Andruhovych's zone, I
realized that very often it is a
language that I want to
say what I want to say.
I read some things out loud because they
sounded like that to me. Andrukhovych is very careful with
his texts. They are such that there
is nothing extra, everything is in its
place, but you can also pick up
some cool words or verbal
constructions from him and in fact, the story in
this story is that your speech was
not robotic, but alive, and it also
happens when you hear a word and think
that I have never used it, it is very important to
define it, practice it, and you can
first use it somewhere in your
post on Instagram, there on Twitter, then
together the second to say see that no one
has burned that you say it voice for the first time
and then you understand it, you
like it, it's apt, it's very cool,
and you use it, but probably the
most important thing is to find your own voice, because,
well, we
re-read Pydmogylny with you. Well, listen to it, it's absolutely my
voice, first of all, it's probably because it's
terribly ironic, it's even so angry in some ways,
but it he chooses the language so coolly and subtly
, which is so fresh, and he
writes about this Kyiv like this. So I
want to go to this division and just
walk through it, walk, walk, this is the kind of
condition I want, which is alive and used, and not in
some dictionary or
sterilely displayed in a window like
the perfect way to say good day
Good day By the way, I still don't agree with
what you can't say Good evening
That's what they say you can't Good evening We're
from Ukraine and Marko Halynevych said how
cool we all are with this, God bless you,
which novel Andruhovich should start with
that when you are asked for
advice, you are asked about some specifics and
not abstract things, well, if in the context of
the transition I would advise you to start with
recreations because the atmosphere in this
novel is very reminiscent of some things
that we have experienced in the last six months. It
seems to me. And in this novel there is simply
an amazing feeling of a carnival and the
opportunity to change the language is also an
opportunity to change your mask in some way
and sometimes even my image, and that's why I think
many people will recognize themselves in the recreations. Who
among those present has read the recreations? Please
raise your hand.
It's very good.
We recommend this text. It's an adventure. Three poets
are going to a poetry festival. They're young
and drunk since the very morning. There's
a lot waiting for them ahead of them. adventure four four
I apologize,
I just always think about the fact that this is a
novel about Bub Boo and that is why there are
four of them, yes, the word there is all that holiday
that the soul needs so much, but at the same time,
mysticism and carnival and a lot of funny phrases
that I really want to take out and
apply. What would you advise? That's
right. Right away, by God, I've been approached with
such questions many times, and I have
prepared answers. I zap I was wondering what you have been
reading lately, you should
start with what you liked, what heroes
do you like, and there were times when people
said to me Well, I decided or decided that now I
will read only in
Ukrainian. I was taught at school, he was a great author,
and I get Mykhailo Starytskyi and start
reading, and I want to explain to a person what is
possible.
they write
in a language that is modern for you, in a language that is understandable to you.
You will not need to look in the dictionary often,
because there, for example, some outdated
form, another ending, some prefix,
it seems that these are all small things, but no,
this stops you, is it because of this that you
exercise continue to rise if you
open, for example, Yurii Andruhovych you
you open Max Kidruk, cool
mass literature,
someone read from the Mexican books that were present, so
look at Yuriy Andruhovych read more,
it is good for Ivano-Frankivsk, we in
Ivano-Frankivsk, it is possible in
Ivano-Frankivsk word Max Kidruk
thrillers or anxieties good anxieties not
redacted a little bit redacted
better thrillers or well, Andrii Kokotyukh is
not advised to do that, but for example Sofya
Andruhovych, by the way, is also a Frankivka of Taras
Prokhaska, who can be read in short
bursts.
it's not bad, it's a
great discovery, but it's an entry point. Well,
maybe not for everyone, but I
will be an entry point for everyone.
Anthology of Ukrainian poetry. And the women of the
gala mages are either huge, so rude from
Tychyna to the desired or the one who is already
desired from the young Ukrainian poetry because
actually this is a text and in which, on the one hand,
you can maneuver between them and
resp to be a server or a surfer on the
wave and on the other hand there will still be a
need to understand the word Because when you
remember poetry you cannot
jump further you need to feel the rhythm of
this word you need to feel it by
touch to be able to read this poetic
line therefore reading poetry This it's also a
very good exercise. You know, if we talk
even without names, but still about emotions,
because in some ways, they started with my emotions, even
though they were talking about legal
documents, nothing works without passion, without
love, and when there is even this conscious
desire to switch to Ukrainian or
improve it you simply
need to find this sphere of love,
something that you will like, and
it won't work here if you don't devote
at least a little time to it, that is, you know. Well, some
people listen to the spat with pleasure and we
see these people, while others are annoyed by it, they don't
like our Ukrainian, and that's
great because I recently looked at the
tops and there you can choose to choose
a color on any topic, but that's how
it should be devoted It's time.
Listen, I have a question for you. Finally,
because it somehow happened that you
asked me today if
we have a law on the functioning of the
Ukrainian language as a
state language.
because it is obvious to us that this
Ukrainian language is important. It is obvious.
But why do we devote more than
an hour to it in our conversation, why do we still
talk about it if there is really a supposed framework
that defines it, why is it important for us to feel the
continuation of meanings or to
say those things that were
said sometimes 100 - 150 years ago in the
context of the Ukrainian language. Today is
2022, because we are doing a podcast with you
about culture today and when
we started doing this podcast in March.
After the war,
we realized this and now we are starting
to live in a new space that we
are trying to clean from everything that
it should have been cleansed of. Long ago,
you and I talked about decolonization from the traces of imperialism,
but in the
comments on Facebook, the historian Sasha
Alfyorov very nicely wrote about the fact that
usually
colonies were much less developed than
metropolises, and therefore you can still argue
with the fact that Ukraine - it really was a
colony, so it is more appropriate to use the
term de-internalization, and I also
really like this idea that we
start where the Empire realizes its
space, its consciousness, its
lists of literature and its libraries,
where to Russify
And actually this whole process also perceives Language
- this is one of those points Maybe even
our whole podcast should start
We should talk about the anxiety
suitcase so that we put it in the
sculptural heritage and the next step
is language because Language is the first thing that
got into our cultural suitcase
not even like that This is some basis of this
cultural suitcase the material from which this
suitcase is sewn, and then talk about everything
else, but m and really postponed this episode
consciously for the end Because we needed
to grow those lean muscles and
find out a lot of other questions until you won't
believe it, but I also thought about the beginning and
about the anxious suitcase because in fact
it was easiest to start today's conversation
with this
most famous probably the phrases of Hera
's guide about the fact that Language is the home of existence
and Well, we all know it. It sounds good,
you can start it on Twitter, but if you
start digging into it, then
24 we all began to look at our home and
think that we can take from there what we
can we save from it what can we
save if the house is destroyed what to do with a
destroyed house and
we want this house to be Ukrainian and
if it is Ukrainian then it is in
Ukrainian We named a lot of
different things today and
you will find about all these vocations in the description of our
episode and on YouTube, Spotify, Apple, Google
podcast and everywhere else, we ask you to put
stars, leave comments, stay
with us, we just read them later
For example, we learn about how our
listeners do not consider Mykola Gogol a
Ukrainian writer, and we are interested in that.
Because we do not do this prompt. For the two of us, we
really want this dialogue.
Because only then is a deeper
understanding of Ukrainian culture born. Well, in the
context of our conversation today, I
I really want
our common home with you to be
truly Ukrainian and I am convinced that we are all taking
a lot of steps to
make it really happen. Nastya,
thank you very much for this conversation and for the
frank story about Ukrainian and
Russian, and I, Bohdana, thank you for that
that we are already 19 episodes together and
we have 20 ahead of us where we will be close to each other
Read Ukrainian poetry about the language This
will be a very interesting episode to me,
next we will have a short
vacation so that we can return with
new forces as usual the vacation of the
school year begins 1 September is a
new academic year,
and we have not yet
finished our previous academic year the year lasts as long
as this war lasts and as long as we do
this prompt Samper tirokozav Ivan Franko
yes yes Well, friends, comradeship, we are
happy to have This live Episode with you in
Ivano-Frankivsk and We thank the prombar for the
fact that he hosted us so much and we had a
very such a glamorous feeling of the
living room audio, I think there is still an opportunity not even
for a virtual audio cocktail And with
such a real normal cocktail
and Thanks to our project partners, read the
project that you all must follow
in Telegram in order to learn about the
news, learn
about the reading club about lectures about culture and literature
in particular because you can draw
a lot of inspiration from there, thank you
[music]